[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]
We'll start with a very quick review of gradient ascent.
سوف نبدأ باستعراض سريع جدًا للتدرج التصاعدي.
In the regression course, Emily went into quite a lot of detail explaining
في دورة الانحدار، قامت إميلي بتقديم شرح تفصيلي للغاية حول
the gradient ascent algorithm, where it comes from, and the details.
خوارزمية التدرج الصعودي، ومن أين يأتي بالتفصيل.
I really recommend you go back to that if you want to
وأنا أوصيك حقًا بالرجوع إليه إذا كنت تريد
remind yourself of where it all comes from.
لتذكير نفسك بأساسات الموضوع.
I'm just going to do a very, very, very quick review here so
فأنا سأقوم فقط بمراجعة سريعة جدًا جدًا هنا حتى
that we remember the fundamentals.
نتذكر الأساسيات.
You can think about the gradient ascent algorithm as
يمكن التفكير في خوارزمية التدرج الصعودي
a kind of hill climbing algorithm.
كنوع من خوارزمية تسلق التل.
If you look at the picture on the left here if you only had one parameter w,
فإذا نظرت إلى الصورة على اليسار هنا إذا كان لديك فقط متغير واحد w،
you can imagine starting at some point, let's say w t with t iteration,
تخيل البدء من نقطة معينة، دعنا نقول t w مع التكرار t،
and then moving little bit uphill to the next parameter, w t+1.
ثم تتحرك مسافة قليلة أعلى التل للمتغير التالي، w t + 1.
And the amount you move from one to the other has to do with this term over here,
والمقدار الذي انتقلته من واحد إلى آخر له علاقة بهذا الطرف هنا،
which is the derivative of our likelihood function with respect to the parameter w.
وهو مشتق دالة الاحتمال الخاصة بنا فيما يتعلق بالمتغير w.
And its computed at the current parameter w t.
ويتم حسابه عند المتغير الحالي w t.
Now remember we have this little extra coefficient parameter eta,
الآن تذكر أن لدينا متغير المعامل الإضافي الصغير هذا η،
which we call the step size.
الذي نسميه الحجم التدريجي.
A little later in the module, we're going to discuss how that step size
بعد ذلك في وقتٍ لاحق في الوحدة، سنقوم بمناقشة كيفية اختيار الحجم التدريجي ذلك
actually gets picked and what effect it has.
في الحقيقة وما هو تأثيره.
But imagine it's given, so you're going to move by eta times the step size.
ولكن تخيل أنه معطى، حيث ستقوم بالتحرك حسب η مضروبًا في الحجم التدريجي.
And so you move here, then you move a little bit, and you keep moving, moving,
وبالتالي تتحرك هنا، ثم تقوم بالتحرك بعض الشيء، وتواصل التحرك أعلى وأعلى
moving, moving uphill, and eventually you get to the top of the hill to the optimum,
صعودًا بالتل، وفي نهاية المطاف تصل إلى أعلى التل إلى النهاية،
which may be, we're going to call w star for right now.
والتي قد تكون، سنقوم بتسميتها w نجمة للآن.
And this is our goal, to get to that very, very top of the hill.
وهذا هو هدفنا، أن نصل إلى أقصى نقطة أعلى التل.
Now that we seen kind of hill climbing the abstract way, getting to that top of
والآن بعد أن رأينا نوعًا من تسلق التل بطريقة مجردة، والوصول إلى أعلى نقطة في
the hill, so we step up until we hit the top here which is w's term.
التل، حيث نواصل التحرك في خطوات حتى نصل إلى الأعلى هنا وهو الحد w.
We can talk about when we know we are done in the interpretive algorithm,
يمكننا أن نتحدث عن متى نعرف أننا قد أتممنا عملنا في الخوارزمية التفسيرية،
when have we converged?
متى حققنا التقارب؟
So you might remember that at the optimum of convex functions and
إذًا قد تتذكر أنه عند النقطة القصوى للدوال المحدبة
what we are dealing with today is a convex function and
ما نتعامل معه اليوم هو دالة محدبة
we talked in quite a bit of detail what that means, but just in general we'll have
وقد تحدثنا بقدرٍ كبيرٍ من التفاصيل حول ما يعنيه ذلك، ولكن فقط بشكل عام سيكون لدينا
the derivative with respect to w for likelihood is going to be equal to
المشتقة بالنسبة إلى w لاحتمالية ستكون مساوية
zero at the optimum here, because that curve flattens out.
للصفر عند النقطة القصوى هنا، نظرً لأن المنحنى يتسطح.
Now, if we could get to the point where the derivative is equal to zero we
الآن، إذا تمكنا من الوصول إلى نقطة حيث تكون المشتقة مساوية للصفر
would be absolutely done.
فسوف نكون قد انتهينا بالتأكيد.
However we're never going to get there exactly, so
ومع ذلك فنحن لن نتمكن من الوصول إلى ذلك تمامًا، وبالتالي
we're going to stop when the derivative is small enough.
سنقوم بالتوقف عندما تصبح المشتقة صغيرة بما يكفي.
So we stop when the derivative with respect to
لذا سنتوقف عندما تكون المشتقة، فيما يتعلق بالمتغير
parameter w computed to recurrent parameter wt.
w محسوبة للمتغير المتكرر wt.
So we'll stop when the derivative is smaller than some
وبالتالي سوف نتوقف عند تصبح المشتقة أصغر من بعض
taller s parameter epsilon.
متغير s الأطول "إبسيلون".
And, you know, sent out some small numbers, 0.001 or something.
وكما تعلمون، نرسل بعض الأرقام الصغيرة، 0.001 أو شيء من هذا القبيل.
Depends on your problem, you'll explore this in your homework.
واعتمادًا على المسألة التي تقوم بحلها، سيتعين عليك استكشاف هذا في واجبك المنزلي.
But keep going, you won't get exactly to the top, but
لكن بمتابعة عملك، لن تصل بالضبط إلى الأعلى، ولكنك
you're going to get pretty close to the top and that will be your w hat.
ستقترب من الوصول إلى الأعلى إلى حدٍ كبير وسوف تكون هذه هي w hat الخاصة بك.
So we'll continue going up and up and
ولذلك سوف نستمر في الذهاب إلى أعلى وأعلى
up until our derivative is sufficiently small.
حتى نصل إلى مشتقة تكون صغيرة بما فيه الكفاية.
Now that was for a one dimensional space, but we have now a large animation
الآن كان هذا من أجل فضاء أحادي البعد، ولكن لدينا الآن صورة متحركة كبيرة
space because we can have thousands of coefficients we're trying to fit.
للفضاء لأنه يمكن أن يكون لدينا آلاف المعاملات التي نسعى لملاءمتها.
So, instead of computing a one dimensional derivative,
لذا، بدلًا من حساب مشتقة أحادية الأبعاد،
we need what's called a gradient.
نحن بحاجة إلى ما يسمى بالتدرج.
And a gradient is just a stacking here of the derivative of l
والتدرج هو فقط تكدس هنا لمشتقة l
with respect to the first parameter the zero.
بالنسبة إلى المعلمة الأولى الصفر.
The partial relative of l with respect to the second parameter of w1 all the way to
العامل النسبي الجزئي لـ l بالنسبة للمتغير الثاني w1 وصولًا إلى
the derivative l the partial derivative with respect to the last parameter wd.
المشتقة l وهي المشتقة الجزئية بالنسبة للمتغير الأخير wd.
So this is a D + 1 dimensional vector for
لذا فهذا هو متجه بعدي D + 1 من أجل
when you have D features.
الاستخدام عندما يكون لديك ميزات D.
And in our case here, if we start from this point and the derivative
وفي حالتنا هنا، إذا بدأنا من هذه النقطة وتم أخذ المشتقة
is taken this way, the gradient is going to be something like this maybe.
بهذه الطريقة، فإن التدرج سيكون شيئًا مثل هذا على الأرجح.
And that's what the gradient correspond to.
وهذا هو ما يتوافق معه التدرج.
And then we're just going to follow that gradient all the way
ثم سنقوم فقط باتباع هذا التدرج على طول الطريق
to the top of the hill.
وصولًا إلى الجزء العلوي من التل.
In a little bit more detail, more pictorially,
وبمزيدٍ من التفصيل، وبشكلٍ تصويري أكثر،
we're going to set some sub-points.
سنقوم بتعيين بعض النقاط الفرعية.
They're mainly heuristics for where to start, but
وهي في الأساس إرشادية لأين يمكننا البدء، ولكن
let's say we start over here and we're just going to follow the gradient.
دعونا نقول إننا سنبدأ هنا وسنقوم فقط باتباع التدرج.
And so on the right side I'm showing you
ولذا على الجانب الأيمن أنا أريك
what are called the contour plots.
ما يسمى برسم الحواف.
And so it corresponds to the level set to the contours of this line.
وهكذا فإنه يتوافق مع المستوى المعين إلى حواف هذا الخط.
So if I start on the left side over here, it's kind of like starting over here.
لذا إذا بدأت على الجانب الأيسر هنا، فسيبدو مماثلًا للابتداء من هنا.
I take a gradient step and
لذا أقوم بأخذ خطوة تدرج
I can keep following it until I get to the optimum here,
ويمكنني أن أستمر في اتباعها حتى أصل إلى النقطة القصوى هنا،
which is going to be rw* and that corresponds to climbing this
والتي ستكون rw* وهي تناظر تسلق هذا
hill until I get to the top of the hill, which is going to be rw*.
التل حتى أصل إلى أعلى التل، الذي سيكون rw*.
And again, Emily went to quite a bit of detail on contour plots and
ومرة أخرى، قامت إميلي بشرح هذا بالكثير من التفاصيل في رسم الحواف
how they relate to that 3D plot.
وكيفية ارتباطها بالرسم ثلاثي الأبعاد هذا.
But that's our goal.
وهذا هو هدفنا.
So finally, just as a reminder,
لذا في النهاية، فقط كتذكرة،
here's what the gradient ascent algorithm looks like.
ها هو ما تبدو عليه خوارزمية التدرج التصاعدي.
You start from some point, w 0, and so you might say w = 0,
يمكنك البدء من نقطة ما، w 0، وبالتالي يمكنك القول w = 0،
or random parameters or something else.
أو متغيرات عشوائية أو أي شيء آخر.
And you just keep following the gradient
ثم تستمر فقط في اتباع التدرج
until the magnitude of the gradient is sufficiently small.
حتى يصبح مقدار التدرج صغيرًا بما فيه الكفاية.
So that's our algorithm, that's going to take us to the optimum.
إذًا هذه هي خوارزميتنا التي سوف تأخذنا إلى الدرجة القصوى.
And it's simplified over here and the eta here is our famous step size.
وقد تم تبسيطها هنا وη هنا هو الحجم التدريجي الشهير الذي نتحدث عنه.
Great, so now we're done for a review of gradient ascent.
رائع، إذًا لقد انتهينا الآن وسنقوم بإجراء مراجعة للتدرج التصاعدي.
[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]